<x>
  <dc>
    <title>Speaking with Vampires: Rumor and History in Colonial Africa</title>
    <creator>Luise White</creator>
    <subject>African Studies</subject>
    <subject>African History</subject>
    <subject>African Studies</subject>
    <subject>Cultural Anthropology</subject>
    <description>During the colonial period, Africans told each other terrifying rumors that
      Africans who worked for white colonists captured unwary residents and took their blood. In
      colonial Tanganyika, for example, Africans were said to be captured by these agents of
      colonialism and hung upside down, their throats cut so their blood drained into huge buckets.
      In Kampala, the police were said to abduct Africans and keep them in pits, where their blood
      was sucked. Luise White presents and interprets vampire stories from East and Central Africa
      as a way of understanding the world as the storytellers did. Using gossip and rumor as
      historical sources in their own right, she assesses the place of such evidence, oral and
      written, in historical reconstruction. White conducted more than 130 interviews for this book
      and did research in Kenya, Uganda, and Zambia. In addition to presenting powerful, vivid
      stories that Africans told to describe colonial power, the book presents an original
      epistemological inquiry into the nature of historical truth and memory, and into their
      relationship to the writing of history.</description>
    <date>5/9/2000</date>
    <type>text</type>
    <identifier>http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft8r29p2ss</identifier>
    <relation>http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation>http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights>Public</rights>
  </dc>
  <xsubject>azzz African Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz African History zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz African Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Cultural Anthropology zzza</xsubject>
  <ntitle>Speaking with Vampires Rumor and History in Colonial Africa</ntitle>
  <lastmod>1071598153</lastmod>
</x>
