<x>
  <dc>
    <title>A Democratic South Africa?: Constitutional Engineering in a Divided Society</title>
    <creator>Donald L. Horowitz</creator>
    <subject>Politics</subject>
    <subject>African Studies</subject>
    <subject>Sociology</subject>
    <subject>Law</subject>
    <description>Can a society as deeply divided as South Africa become democratic? In a most timely
      work, Donald L. Horowitz, author of the acclaimed Ethnic Groups in Conflict, points to the
      conditions that make democracy an improbable outcome in South Africa. At the same time, he
      identifies ways to overcome these obstacles, and he describes institutions that offer
      constitution makers the best chance for a democratic future.South Africa is generally
      considered an isolated case, a country unlike any other. Drawing on his extensive experience
      of racially and ethnically divided societies, however, Horowitz brings South Africa back into
      African and comparative politics. Experience gained in Nigeria, Botswana, Zimbabwe, and other
      divided societies around the world is relevant because, as South Africa leaves apartheid
      behind, it will still confront problems of pluralism: racial, ethnic, and ideological.
      Countries like South Africa, Horowitz argues, must develop institutions capable of coping with
      such divisions.Reviewing an array of constitutional proposals for South Africa - group rights,
      consociation, partition, binationalism, and an enhanced role for the judiciary - Horowitz
      shows that most are inappropriate for the country's problems, or else run afoul of some major
      ideological taboo. Institutions that are both apt and acceptable do exist, however. These are
      premised on the need to create incentives for accommodation across group lines. In the final
      chapter, Horowitz makes a major contribution to the theory of democratization as he considers
      how commitments to democracy might be extracted even from political groups with undemocratic
      objectives.Ranging skillfully across studies of social distance and stereotypes, electoral and
      party systems, constitutions and judiciaries, conflict and accommodation, and negotiation and
      democratization, Horowitz displays a broad comparative vision. His innovative study will
      change the way theorists and practitioners approach the task of making democracy work in
      difficult conditions.</description>
    <date>1/7/1991</date>
    <type>text</type>
    <identifier>http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft0f59n6zd</identifier>
    <relation>http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation>http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights>Public</rights>
  </dc>
  <xsubject>azzz Politics zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz African Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Sociology zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Law zzza</xsubject>
  <ntitle>Democratic South Africa Constitutional Engineering in a Divided Society</ntitle>
</x>
