<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<document xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf">
    <title xtf:meta="true">Asylia: Territorial Inviolability in the Hellenistic World</title>
    <creator xtf:meta="true">Kent J. Rigsby</creator>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Classics</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Ancient History</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Politics</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Classical History</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Classical Religions</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Classical Politics</subject>
    <description xtf:meta="true">In the Hellenistic period certain Greek temples and cities came to be declared "sacred and inviolable." Asylia was the practice of declaring religious places precincts of asylum, meaning they were immune to violence and civil authority. The evidence for this phenomenon - mainly inscriptions and coins - is scattered in the published record. The material has never been collected and presented in one publication until now.Kent J. Rigsby lays out these documents and discusses their historical implications in a substantial introduction. He argues that while a hopeful intention of military neutrality lay behind the institution of asylum, the declarations did not in fact change military behavior. Instead, "declared inviolability" became a civic and religious honor for which cities across the Greek world competed during the third to first centuries B.C.</description>
    <date xtf:meta="true">19970328</date>
    <type xtf:meta="true">text</type>
    <identifier xtf:meta="true">http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft2s2004r1</identifier>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights xtf:meta="true">UCOnly</rights>
    <div1 type="chapter" rend="Heading-Heading2B" id="d0e727">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <pb id="JD_Page_1" n="1"/>
        <p>A modern commonplace holds that Greek civic religion after the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi> was an empty shell, traditional forms followed without emotion, and that the Greeks' true longings expressed themselves in the mystery religions and other novelties or in philosophy—in phenomena at once more personal and more universal than the cults of the old gods. This view owes much to hindsight, our desire to explain the rise of Christianity. An enduring source of strength of pagan cults was precisely their local and formal character: the gods of one's own city and country watched over places familiar and significant, bound up with the life cycle of the individual and the group. The holy places of one's land had each been touched by a particular god for reasons known to the community. Here were powerful roots, with which the new religions of Roman times offered little to compete, until the rise of the cult of saints. Civic religion, polytheism, would decline only with civic life itself in late antiquity.</p>
        <p>In the Hellenistic period, certain places, either temples with their precincts or whole cities with their territories, were declared by foreign states to be "sacred and inviolable" in honor of the city's tutelary god. This episode in the history of Greek civic religion and Greek diplomacy is the concern of the present volume.</p>
        <div2 type="ss1" rend="Heading-Heading3" id="d0e738">
            <head>Sacred Space</head>
            <p>
              <hi rend="italic">Est locus</hi> . . . The literature of the Greeks and Romans provides rich testimony to their emotional response to sacred places, where ritual, myth, dedicatory objects, or even natural setting<ref target="fnd0e1889" type="fnoteref">1</ref> betokened the presence or past action of a god.</p>
            <note id="fnd0e1889" type="footnote" n="1">
              <p>
                 <hi rend="italic">Stat vetus et multos incaedua silva per annos; credibile est illi numen inesse loco</hi> (Ov. <hi rend="italic">Am.</hi> 3.1-2; cf. <hi rend="italic">Fast.</hi> 3.295-296).</p>
            </note>
            <pb id="JD_Page_2" n="2"/>
            <p>Many religions, in separating the sacred from the profane,<ref target="fnd0e1924" type="fnoteref">2</ref> apply this distinction to space; places attributed to the divine are in some measure under the god's authority, and in them mortals may be bound by rules that do not pertain in secular space. In ancient Greece this boundary was especially strong: as we see in many anecdotes from both life and literature, anyone who entered a temple precinct or clasped an altar or even achieved some other physical connection with sacred space<ref target="fnd0e1934" type="fnoteref">3</ref> was to be immune from violence, for he had put himself at the discretion of the god rather than of man.<ref target="fnd0e1944" type="fnoteref">4</ref> Anyone could do it, at any sacred place. Other religions can be cited in which this barrier is less forceful or more selective. In Republican Rome such a "right of asylum" was an anomaly, specially conceded to only one or two temples: immunity from secular intrusion was not automatically a property of sacred space. Similarly, in pharaonic Egypt, temples seem not to have enjoyed immunity from the civil authorities. So is it also in the modern West: the rise of the secular state was accompanied by the gradual, and often disputed, rejection of the late antique and medieval tradition of the right of asylum of Christian churches.<ref target="fnd0e1951" type="fnoteref">5</ref> Today in the United States, a fugitive from the law will gain no immunity by fleeing to a church, synagogue, or mosque.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> 22, Roman authorities feared that the right of asylum practiced in their Greek provinces posed a threat to civic tranquility. Moderns might well sympathize; exemption from the power of the state seems on its face subversive to good order. It is worth observing, therefore, that selective territorial immunity from the law is a widely attested practice, despite which the needs of public order are successfully met. Early modern London had various neighborhoods that served as debtors' asylums, from which the instruments of public authority were excluded. These areas were left to govern themselves, and they maintained strict admissions policies; the last of them was abolished by act of Parliament in</p>
            <note id="fnd0e1924" type="footnote" n="2">
              <p> For Greek vocabulary on the distinction see W. R. Connor, <hi rend="italic">AncSoc</hi> 19 (1988) 161-188. For the distinction in Christianity see R. A. Markus, <hi rend="italic">JECS</hi> 2 (1994) 257-271.</p>
            </note>
        </div2>
    </div1>
</document>