<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<document xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf">
    <title xtf:meta="yes" xtf:tokenize="no">The Opening of the Apartheid Mind: Options for the New South Africa</title>
    <creator xtf:meta="yes" xtf:tokenize="no">Heribert Adam and Kogila Moodley</creator>
    <subject xtf:meta="yes">African Studies</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Politics</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">African History</subject>
    <description xtf:meta="true">Refusing to be governed by what is fashionable or inoffensive, Heribert Adam and Kogila Moodley frankly address the passions and rationalities that drive politics in post-apartheid South Africa. They argue that the country's quest for democracy is widely misunderstood and that public opinion abroad relies on stereotypes of violent tribalism and false colonial analogies.Adam and Moodley criticize the personality cult surrounding Nelson Mandela and the accolades accorded F. W. de Klerk. They reject the black-versus-white conflict and substitute sober analysis and strategic pragmatism for the moral outrage that typifies so much writing about South Africa. Believing that the best expression of solidarity emanates from sympathetic but candid criticism, they pose challenging questions for the African National Congress and Nelson Mandela. They give in-depth coverage to political violence, the ANC-South African Communist Party alliance, Inkatha, and other controversial topics as well.The authors do not propose a solution that will guarantee a genuinely democratic South Africa. What they offer is an understanding of the country's social conditions and political constraints, and they sketch options for both a new South Africa and a new post-Cold War foreign policy for the whole of southern Africa. The importance of this book is as immediate as today's headlines.</description>
    <date xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">19930628</date>
    <type xtf:meta="true">text</type>
    <identifier xtf:meta="true">http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft958009mm</identifier>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights xtf:meta="true">Public</rights>
    <div1 id="ch1" type="chapter" n="1" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete">
        <head type="main">Colonialism, Communalism, and Democracy</head>
        <head type="sub">South Africa in Comparative Perspective</head>
        <div2 id="s1.1.1" type="ss1" rend="ornament" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete">
            <head type="main">The Global Relevance of South Africa</head>
            <p>It is now conventional wisdom that after the end of the cold war, Africa as a continent has become marginalized to the extent of sliding into what a French official called the "conservatory of the ills of humanity."<ref target="bn1.1" id="d0e1044" type="noteref" targOrder="U">1</ref> Benign neglect of a seemingly hopeless irrelevancy characterizes outside attitudes. Even the long overdue World Bank-induced redemocratization of the continent does little to solve the problem of establishing order, stability, growth, and civility in weak states; in fact, the removal of tyrants may make life worse when successors fight each other in endless civil wars. After the abolition of the apartheid system, for example, the number of political killings in South Africa has tripled and the economic decline has accelerated.</p>
            <p>Yet it is precisely the immensity of the problems of the "forgotten continent" that makes Africa relevant globally. The category "Third World" may indeed have had meaning only in the context of the global cold war division, as some scholars argue.<ref target="bn1.2" id="d0e1049" type="noteref" targOrder="U">2</ref> With the former Soviet Union descending into political and economic chaos, a more relevant classification groups the affluent, economically stable states (North America, Western Europe, Japan, and the newly industrialized Asian countries) into one competing trading bloc. A second bloc consists of states with some resources and potential for growth as well as kinship ties and ideological affinities with the first-tier states; this second bloc includes most of Latin America, some states in the Middle East and Asia, and South Africa. Relegated to the third category are politically volatile countries without resources and claims on or hopes for Western assistance: sub-Saharan Africa, the southern Balkan states, the Caucasus, and most of South Asia. They are increasingly left to their own misery, at best the recipients of mere charity.</p>
            <p>This new North-South division ignores former ideological contests and is characterized by access to the dominant economic resources (credits, markets, and political support) of the first bloc. Yet the powerful North neglects the powerless South at its own peril, for the importance of the South lies in its very weakness, in its capacity to destabilize the entire globe. The worldwide effects of environmental degradation, the streams of economic refugees into the islands of comparative affluence, the spread of AIDS and other diseases, the slaughter enacted in the name of religious or nationalist fundamentalism-what happens among the have-nots eventually affects the haves. It is this potential to cause chaos, or what Dieter Senghaas refers to as <hi rend="italic">Chaosmacht,</hi> that constitutes the power of the powerless.</p>
            <p>South Africa embodies the North-South conflict in one country, albeit with a decisive difference. Unlike Western Europe, South Africa cannot build new iron curtains to keep its haves insulated from the have-nots. The highways and railways leading out of Cape Town, Johannesburg, or Durban cut right through the huge slums of Khayelitsha, Soweto, and Kwa Mashu. While the violence of deprivation can be deflected on its victims, their struggles increasingly spill over into the fortifications of the affluent, who cannot enjoy their privileges when the murder rate in Johannesburg is three times higher than that of the worst American city. Especially when the stability and security of the white minority depends directly on the cooperative labor of the majority, its brutalization cannot be contained beyond the factory gates.</p>
            <p>South Africa thus constitutes a laboratory for the new global compromise between the North and the South, whether in race relations, multicultural education, or economic cooperation between capital and labor. The society will either bring forth new forms of cooperative development and legitimacy or will disintegrate through ethnic violence and costly repression. Europe increasingly perceives the South as burdensome; begging strangers are to be held at bay. Because the people of South Africa share a common citizenship, history, and economy, they cannot retreat from or postpone the challenge. South Africans cannot divorce each other through partition without destroying their source of wealth. Unlike the centrifugal ethnoregionalism in the rest of the world, centripetal forces in South Africa bind the antagonistic segments into a common state. The poorer regions are dependent on transfer payments. It is out of this imperative that the world's most backward political system of legal segregation could perhaps develop into an advanced model for the gradual solution of the North-South cleavage through unitary federalism with regional autonomy.</p>
        </div2>
    </div1>
</document>