<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<document xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf">
    <title xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">The Problems of a Political Animal: Community, Justice, and Conflict in Aristotelian Political Thought</title>
    <creator xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">Bernard R. Yack</creator>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Politics</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Philosophy</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Political Theory</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Social and Political Thought</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Social Theory</subject>
    <description xtf:meta="true">A bold new interpretation of Aristotelian thought is central to Bernard Yack's provocative new book. He shows that for Aristotle, community is a conflict-ridden fact of everyday life, as well as an ideal of social harmony and integration. From political justice and the rule of law to class struggle and moral conflict, Yack maintains that Aristotle intended to explain the conditions of everyday political life, not just, as most commentators assume, to represent the hypothetical achievements of an idealistic "best regime."By showing how Aristotelian ideas can provide new insight into our own political life, Yack makes a valuable contribution to contemporary discourse and debate. His work will excite interest among a wide range of social, moral, and political theorists.</description>
    <date xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">19930809</date>
    <type xtf:meta="true">text</type>
    <identifier xtf:meta="true">http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft7r29p1pf</identifier>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">UCOnly</rights>
    <div1 type="chapter" id="d0e55">
        <pb id="JD_Page_1" n="1"/>
        <head rend="Heading-Heading2B">Introduction</head>
        <p>The shared sentiments and commitments that constitute a community are often the source of its deepest conflicts. Anyone who has lived in a family rather than merely longed for a home knows that all too well. Strangers may cheat you, but only brothers or sisters, comrades or colleagues can betray you. In the end, intense and ugly forms of distrust and conflict are part of the price we pay for the pleasures of communal life.</p>
        <p>Aristotle, unlike many of his contemporary followers, is deeply aware of the special conflicts associated with human communities. The intensity of our conflicts, he notes, increases with the closeness of our relationships. Anger is something that individuals "express more strongly against their companions, when they think they have been treated unjustly.... Hence the sayings 'Cruel are the wars of brothers' and 'Those who love extravagantly will hate extravagantly as well.' ... And it is reasonable," Aristotle concludes, "that this should happen. For, in addition to the injury, they also consider themselves robbed of this [companionship]" (<hi rend="italic">Politics</hi> [hereafter <hi rend="italic">Pol.</hi> ] 1328a10).<ref target="fnd0e549" type="fnoteref">1</ref>
        </p>
        <p>Critics of modern liberal democracies often invoke Aristotle's understanding of political community when they complain that our political</p>
        <note id="fnd0e549" type="footnote" n="1">
           <p> See Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> 1379b2 and <hi rend="italic">Nicomachean Ethics</hi> 1160a3, for similar remarks. Like Georg Simmel, Aristotle is familiar with "the wholly disproportionate violence to which normally well-controlled people can be moved within their relations to those closest to them"; G. Simmel, <hi rend="italic"> Conflict,</hi> 43-44.</p>
        </note>
        <pb id="JD_Page_2" n="2"/>
        <p>life is nothing but "civil war carried on by other means," "a war of all against all ... we make for ourselves, not out of whole cloth but out of an intentional distortion of our social natures."<ref target="fnd0e581" type="fnoteref">2</ref> But for Aristotle political community signifies a conflict-ridden reality rather than a vision of lost or future harmony. It is the scene of political conflict rather than its remedy. All the cruel, mindless, and selfish actions that we, sadly, associate with ordinary political life are included prominently among "the political things" (<hi rend="italic">ta politika</hi> ) that Aristotle sets out to study; he does not restrict his study to just the occasional moments of warmth and heroism. Just as there are peaks of virtue and cooperation that can be found only among citizens, so there are forms of distrust, conflict, and competition that only citizens experience. Accordingly, an Aristotelian account of politics must explain the problems of political life as well as its proudest achievements. And it must, as I try to show, use the bonds created by political community to help explain these problems rather than treat them as a consequence of the absence or weakening of communal bonds themselves. In other words, Aristotle insists on what we might call a communitarian account of political conflict and competition.</p>
        <p>The very idea of a communitarian account of political conflict and competition may seem strange or paradoxical, given the general association of the term <hi rend="italic">communitarian</hi> with aspirations toward social harmony and integration. Most contemporary communitarians see political community as a remedy for political conflict rather than one of its sources. But if, as communitarians insist, our shared practices and sentiments largely constitute our identity and character, then it seems sensible to look, as I suggest Aristotle does, to the way in which we share things in order to help explain our continuing social and political conflicts.</p>
        <p>Aristotle also insists that a proper understanding of the achievements and opportunities made possible by political community must take due note of the imperfect and conflict-ridden conditions in which those achievements arise. He argues that although the political community comes into being for the sake of survival and comfort, its highest and final purpose is to enable us to lead the good life of rational and virtuous behavior. In particular, the political community provides us with the laws that help us acquire the virtues and the shared practices that</p>
        <note id="fnd0e581" type="footnote" n="2">
           <p> A. MacIntyre, <hi rend="italic">After Virtue,</hi> 263; B. Barber, <hi rend="italic">Strong Democracy,</hi> 75.</p>
        </note>
    </div1>
</document>