<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<document xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf">
    <title xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">Thirty-Eight Witnesses: The Kitty Genovese Case</title>
    <creator xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">A.M. Rosenthal</creator>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Politics</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Sociology</subject>
    <subject xtf:meta="true">Urban Studies</subject>
    <description xtf:meta="true">In a decade scarred by some of the worst tragedies in this country's history, March 13, 1964, stands apart from the other atrocities, not because of the identity of the victim - whose name was not Kennedy, King, or Malcolm - but because of the circumstances. Kitty Genovese was a 28-year-old middle-class woman from Kew Gardens, Queens, whose murder was distinguished by the presence of thirty-eight witnesses who did nothing to stop the series of attacks that would claim her life.Thirty years later the Kitty Genovese murder still presses us to ask a litany of questions: Why did these people fail to act? What does it say about the conditions of contemporary urban life? Would it happen today? First published over thirty years ago, Thirty-Eight Witnesses remains a social document that warrants close and repeated examination. The account of the story, as related by one of the best-known and most controversial newspaper professionals in the country, has the added dimension of being part memoir, part investigative journalism, and part public service. In an updated preface that incorporates the most recent developments in the case, A.M. Rosenthal examines why the murder of Kitty Genovese still has the power to shock in a world jaded by news of urban violence.</description>
    <date xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">19990331</date>
    <type xtf:meta="true">text</type>
    <identifier xtf:meta="true">http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft8v19p2pw</identifier>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation xtf:meta="true">http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="no">Public</rights>
    <special xtf:meta="true" xtf:tokenize="false">A</special>
    <div1 id="d0e123" type="fmsec" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete">
        <head type="main" rend="Heading-Heading2">INTRODUCTION TO PAPERBACK EDITION</head>
        <p>Soon after I returned from years of reporting in far places and was beginning my work as a newspaper editor in New York City, I wrote a small book about a woman called Catherine Genovese.</p>
        <p>I had never met her or anybody who had known her. I knew very little about her except that she was twenty-eight years old when I first heard her name, that she was an Italian American with a thin, serious face and worked tending bar in a middle-class neighborhood in the borough of Queens. Her parents were unhappy that she lived alone. They wanted her to live with them in their house in a suburb of New York City.</p>
        <p>That was thirty-four years ago, as I write. Even now, I do not know a great deal more about her life. Her life was not the reason that I wrote about her, or that millions of people came to know her name and have never forgotten it, and that for more than three decades she has affected my life and work, which for most journalists are pretty much the same thing.</p>
        <pb id="JD_Page_viii" n="viii"/>
        <p>I was interested only in the manner of her dying. She died in the early hours of March 13, 1964, outside the small apartment house in Queens where she lived, as neighbors heard her scream her last half hour away and did nothing, nothing at all, to give her succor or even cry alarm.</p>
        <p>Her death, not her life, has been written about all these years since it took place. It has been the subject of lectures and seminars in universities, of sermons in churches and synagogues, of several television dramas, and of at least ten plays. One opened in Los Angeles and another in Buenos Aires; other writers are working still on the story of Catherine Genovese. I know because they write to me. They seek some new insight from me, and I from them. We keep seeking, so strong is the memory of Catherine Genovese-the memory, that is, of the way of her dying.</p>
        <p>Her name, once known only to her family and the people she served at the bar, has taken on instantly understood meaning to all who have heard it. The Kitty Genovese story, the Genovese case, has become both a quick, puffy cliche for apathy and cowardice about the suffering of others, and an intellectual and religious puzzlement: what does it mean to me?</p>
        <p>To me, you, we. That is the power of the Gen-</p>
        <pb id="JD_Page_ix" n="ix"/>
        <p rend="noindent">ovese matter. It talks to us not about her, a subject that was barely of fleeting interest to us, but about ourselves, a subject never out of our minds.</p>
        <p>Nor do we think much about the man who stabbed her to death and then lay down on her body to ejaculate. Even the neighbors who heard her scream and cry for life, who never walked down the stairs to help or even called the police, are not thought of as individuals but as a clump-the thirty-eight witnesses, we call them and always will-not this one and that one and the other, but the clump. The words mean callousness and cowardice beyond our comprehension; we say that.</p>
        <p>The witnesses have not told us much about themselves. Why should they? Go away, get the hell away from my door, they told reporters. We know that they were perfectly ordinary people, skilled workers, tradesmen, people making a living, not bothering anybody, never known to be cruel or cowardly. If we did know more about some of them, would it tell us what we wanted to know, and was that the reason we will not allow the death of Catherine Genovese to escape us? I do not think so.</p>
        <p>In the first days after I was involved in the Genovese case, I thought the question and answer were</p>
    </div1>
</document>