<x>
  <dc>
    <title>The Velvet Glove: Paternalism and Conflict in Gender, Class, and Race Relations</title>
    <creator>Mary Jackman</creator>
    <subject>Sociology</subject>
    <subject>Social Problems</subject>
    <subject>American Studies</subject>
    <subject>Ethnic Studies</subject>
    <subject>Gender Studies</subject>
    <description>This landmark study analyzes and compares the ideologies that develop among unequal
      social groups. Mary Jackman employs a unique national survey to investigate all three of the
      most prominent relations of inequality in the United States: gender, class, and race. Where
      other scholars have emphasized conflict as the emblem of intergroup oppression, Jackman
      proposes a theory in which both dominant and subordinate groups maneuver to avoid open
      hostility as they strive to control resources within the confines of their mutual
      relationship.Hostility, Jackman points out, creates resistance in a relationship. Dominant
      groups therefore try to preempt the use of force by following a velvet-glove strategy of
      "sweet persuasion." They are drawn especially to the ideological mold of paternalism, in which
      the coercion of subordinates is grounded in love rather than hate. Dominant-group members
      pronounce authoritatively on the needs and welfare of all and then profess to "provide" for
      those needs. Love, affection, and praise are offered to subordinates on strict condition that
      they comply with the terms of the unequal relationship. Whether in the home or in the arena of
      class or race relations, paternalism wraps control and authority in an ideological cocoon in
      which discriminatory actions are defined as benevolent and affection is made contingent on
      compliance.Jackman's emphasis on the practice of coercive love in race, class, and gender
      relations is sure to generate controversy and further research. Sociologists, psychologists,
      political scientists, and anyone interested in group ideology will find here a provocative
      challenge to conventional views.</description>
    <date>4/11/1994</date>
    <type>text</type>
    <identifier>http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft958009k3</identifier>
    <relation>http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation>http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights>Public</rights>
  </dc>
  <xsubject>azzz Sociology zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Social Problems zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz American Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Ethnic Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Gender Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <ntitle>Velvet Glove Paternalism and Conflict in Gender Class and Race Relations</ntitle>
  <lastmod>1071598027</lastmod>
</x>
