<x>
  <dc>
    <title>Roots of North Indian Shi'ism in Iran and Iraq: Religion and State in Awadh, 1722-1859</title>
    <creator>J. R. I. Cole</creator>
    <subject>Asian Studies</subject>
    <description>In this pioneering study of the Twelver Shi'i branch of Islam prevalent in Iraq and
      Iran, J. R. I. Cole traces the influence of Shi'i rule on the development of religious
      communalism and conflict in the North Indian State of Awadh (Oudh). He also examines the
      relationship of the Shi'i clergy to the state and the clerical reaction to British imperialism
      and capitalism.Based on research in rare manuscripts and in archives, the book reveals that
      the Shi'i clergy advocated policies that caused resentment among Sunnis and Hindus, thereby
      promoting religious communalism and setting the stage for modern communal conflict. The Shi'i
      learned men took government posts in support of Awadh's Shi'i nawabs and shahs; Awadh state
      support, in turn, helped transform Shi'ism from a persecuted "sect" to a dominant, if still
      minority, religious establishment.Sociologically, the book draws attention to the specific
      role of the state in defining "sect" and "church." It also argues the importance of class
      divisions within the Shi'i community, showing that the dominant clerical ideology was often
      not accepted by the laboring strata. Cole's study supports the view that Muslim communalism in
      Northern India had genuine historical roots and was not simply an elite strategy of modern
      Muslim politicians. Contrary to the arguments of some writers and to the image projected by
      Iran's current ayatullahs, he claims that most Shi'i clergy did not play a role of opposition
      to the state.</description>
    <date>2/3/1989</date>
    <type>text</type>
    <identifier>http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft0f59n6r9</identifier>
    <relation>http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation>http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights>Public</rights>
  </dc>
  <xsubject>azzz Asian Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <ntitle>Roots of North Indian Shiism in Iran and Iraq Religion and State in Awadh 17221859</ntitle>
  <ncreator>Cole, J. R. I.</ncreator>
  <lastmod>1071598132</lastmod>
</x>
