<x>
  <dc>
    <title>The Voice in the Margin: Native American Literature and the Canon</title>
    <creator>Arnold Krupat </creator>
    <subject>Native American Studies</subject>
    <subject>American Literature</subject>
    <description>In its consideration of American Indian literature as a rich and exciting body of
      work, The Voice in the Margin invites us to broaden our notion of what a truly inclusive
      American literature might be, and of how it might be placed in relation to an international -
      a "cosmopolitan" - literary canon. The book comes at a time when the most influential national
      media have focused attention on the subject of the literary canon. They have made it an issue
      not merely of academic but of general public concern, expressing strong opinions on the
      subject of what the American student should or should not read as essential or core texts. Is
      the literary canon simply a given of tradition and history, or is it, and must it be,
      constantly under construction? The question remains hotly contested to the present
      moment.Arnold Krupat argues that the literary expression of the indigenous peoples of the
      United States has claims on us to more than marginal attention. Demonstrating a firm grasp of
      both literary history and contemporary critical theory, he situates Indian literature,
      traditional and modern, in a variety of contexts and categories. His extensive knowledge of
      the history and current theory of ethnography recommends the book to anthropologists and
      folklorists as well as to students and teachers of literature, both canonical and
      noncanonical. The materials covered, the perspectives considered, and the learning displayed
      all make The Voice in the Margin a major contribution to the exciting field of contemporary
      cultural studies.</description>
    <date>11/15/1989</date>
    <type>text</type>
    <identifier>http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft2g5004sk</identifier>
    <relation>http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation>http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights>Public</rights>
  </dc>
  <xsubject>azzz Native American Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz American Literature zzza</xsubject>
  <ntitle>Voice in the Margin Native American Literature and the Canon</ntitle>
  <ncreator>Krupat, Arnold</ncreator>
  <lastmod>1071598148</lastmod>
</x>
