<x>
  <dc>
    <title>Mass Mediations: New Approaches to Popular Culture in the Middle East and Beyond</title>
    <creator>Walter Armbrust, editor</creator>
    <subject>Middle Eastern Studies</subject>
    <subject>Anthropology</subject>
    <subject>Cultural Anthropology</subject>
    <subject>Media Studies</subject>
    <subject>Music</subject>
    <subject>Cinema and Performance Arts</subject>
    <description>Offering a stimulating diversity of perspectives, this collection examines how
      popular culture through mass media defines the scale and character of social interaction in
      the Middle East. The contributors approach popular culture broadly, with an interest in how it
      creates new scales of communication and new dimensions of identity that affect economics,
      politics, aesthetics, and performance. Reflected in these essays is the fact that mass media
      are as ubiquitous in Cairo and Karachi as in Los Angeles and Detroit. From Persian popular
      music in Beverly Hills to Egyptians' reaction to a recent film on Gamal Abdel Nasser; from
      postmodern Turkish novels to the music of an Israeli transsexual singer, the essays illustrate
      the multiple contexts of modern cultural production. The unfolding of modernity in colonial
      and postcolonial societies has been little analyzed until now. In addressing transnational
      aspects of Middle Eastern societies, the contributors also challenge conventional assumptions
      about the region and its relation to the West. The volume will have wide appeal both to Middle
      Eastern scholars and to readers interested in global and cultural studies.</description>
    <date>9/19/2000</date>
    <type>text</type>
    <identifier>http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft8k4008kx</identifier>
    <relation>http://www.ucpress.edu/</relation>
    <relation>http://escholarship.cdlib.org/</relation>
    <rights>Public</rights>
  </dc>
  <xsubject>azzz Middle Eastern Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Anthropology zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Cultural Anthropology zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Media Studies zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Music zzza</xsubject>
  <xsubject>azzz Cinema and Performance Arts zzza</xsubject>
  <ntitle>Mass Mediations New Approaches to Popular Culture in the Middle East and Beyond</ntitle>
  <ncreator>Armbrust, Walter</ncreator>
  <lastmod>1071598038</lastmod>
</x>
